Berkeley, CA. Grace North Church records, 1891-2016. RG5473
Congregational Library & Archives
Berkeley, CA. Grace North Church records, 1891-2016.
Congregational Library & Archives
North Congregational Church (Berkeley, Calif.)
Congregational Church of North Berkeley (Berkeley, Calif.)
Grace North Church (Berkeley, Calif.)
RG5473
5.31 Cubic Feet (7 boxes)
The North Grace Church's origins begin at a meeting on June 28, 1892 with twenty-four "charter members." The newly formed church, then called the Congregational Church of North Berkeley, would be led by Rev. David F. Taylor. The church would close as North Congregational Church in 1992. The church would make a return in 1995 as Grace North Church and remain open until 2023. This collection contains various records from across Grace North Church and includes topics like vital statistics, church reports and meeting minutes, auxiliary organizations, finances, histories and publications, and church buildings.
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Ric Reed, secretary of North Grace Church in August 2023; 2023-38.
Historical Note
The North Grace Church's origins begin at a meeting on June 28, 1892, moderated by Rev. J.K. McLean and Rev. E.F. Dinsmore as the scribe. At this meeting, articles of faith and a covenant were accepted by twenty-six members. Two people would drop shortly after, leaving the new church with twenty-four "charter members." The newly formed church, then called the Congregational Church of North Berkeley, would be led by Rev. David F. Taylor. A new church building would be dedicated on May 21, 1893, at the southwest corner of Cedar and Oxford Streets.
The Church would be officially incorporated in California on September 25, 1895. The church's membership would be around 147 members in 1904, twelve years after being formed. The following year, the church building was moved to the rear of the lot and elevated to house Sunday School rooms, pastor's study, and parlor. Out of this Sunday School grew the Chinese branch of North Church which would go on to become Berkeley Chines Church in 1914.
The now called North Church steadily moved through the Depression and into the 1940s. On September 7, 1944, the church building was destroyed in a fire. The congregation would meet at various other locations for a couple of years until a new building was completed on January 16, 1949. Much of the process was led by Rev. Eugene Haynes alongside numerous other members of the community.
In 1960, the North Congregational Church decided to join the United Church of Christ. This membership would last until 1968, when the church would join the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches. The church would progress through the 1970s, closing their Sunday School in 1975 due to low attendance. The church's overall membership would see decline through the 1980s, though benevolent giving continued to be strong. Continued decline in membership led to the church agreeing to close its doors in 1992, giving the land over to the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches.
The closure in 1992 was not the end of the story and in 1995 fourteen former members of the North Congregational Church asked the Grace Institute to join and form a new church which would eventually be called Grace North Church. The Institute was filled with former members of the North Congregational Church and worshipped in the same building. Thus, the legacy of North Congregational Church was taken on by the Grace North Church. They rejoined the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches in June of 1995. This Grace North Church would continue to serve the community until it officially closed in 2023.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains various records from across Grace North Church and includes topics like vital statistics, church reports and meeting minutes, auxiliary organizations, finances, histories and publications, and church buildings.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into five series from the Grace North Church. The Church Reports and Meeting Minutes series and the Auxiliary Organizations series have been further divdied into subseries. All of the series and subseries have been arranged into chronological order.
Series 1: Vital Statistics, 1891-2016
Series 2: Church Reports and Meeting Minutes, 1892-2010
Sub-series 1: Meeting Minutes, 1892-2010
Sub-series 2: Reports, 1914-2005
Series 3: Auxiliary Organizations, 1899-1955, 1989-1996
Sub-series 1: Ladies' Aid Society, 1899-1924
Sub-series 2: Bay Association, 1921-1955
Series 4: Finances, 1937-1973
Series 5: Histories and Publications, 1942-1959, 1990-1998
Series 6: Building and Architecture, 1948-1966, 1995-2010
Bibliography
North Congregational Church: A History of 75 Years. Berkeley: Andlyn Press, 1967.
Guest books.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Church records and registers.; Church finance.; Church history.; Church membership.; Church buildings.; Christian education.; Baptismal records.; Grace North Church (Berkeley, Calif.); Congregational Church of North Berkeley (Berkeley, Calif.); North Congregational Church (Berkeley, Calif.); Berkeley (Calif.) -- Church history.
- Vital Statistics, 1891-2016; 19 Items (2 folders, 17 volumes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the vital statistics from the church and include baptisms, admissions, dismissions, memorials and various guest books.
  - Vital Statistics and Meeting Minutes, 1891-1906 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Admissions and Dismissions, 1892-1926 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Membership, 1892-1926 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Memorial records, 1897, 1948-1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Vital Statistics and Meeting Minutes, 1907-1914 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Vital Statistics and Meeting Minutes, 1915-1926 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Vital Statistics and Meeting Minutes, 1927-1945 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Guest Book, 1938-1949 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Vital Statistics and Meeting Minutes, 1945-1960 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Guest Book, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Vital Statistics, 1949-1959 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Guest Book, 1954-1960 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Vital Statistics and Meeting Minutes, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Guest Book, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Vital Statistics and Meeting Minutes, 1968-1986 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Guest Book, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Memorial records, 1971-1991 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Guest Book, 2006-2010 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Baptismal Register, 2006-2016 (Box 7, Volume 1)
- Church Reports and Meeting Minutes, 1892-2010; 38 Items (24 folders, 14 volumes)
  This series contains church reports, annual reports, and meeting minutes from a variety of different boards and committees.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1892-2010; 24 Items (11 folders, 13 volumes)
    This subseries contains meeting minutes from the Board of Trustees, Board of Directors, Mission Society, Advisory Committee, Parish Meetings, and a special meeting on disbanding the North Congregational Church.
    - Board of Trustee minutes, 1892-1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1899-1902 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - Mission Society records, 1900-1908 (Box 3, Volume 6)
    - Board of Trustees minutes, 1903-1910 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - Board of Trustees minutes, 1911-1915 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    - Board of Trustees minutes, 1915-1924 (Box 2, Volume 4)
    - Advisory Committee, 1916-1927 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondences, 1916-1933 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Board of Trustees minutes, 1924-1938 (Box 2, Volume 5)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Volume 6)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1949-1956 (Box 2, Volume 7)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Volume 8)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Volume 9)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Volume 10)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Volume 11)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Volume 12)
    - Board of Directors minutes, July 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Meeting on disbanding North Congregational Church, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Regular meeting minutes, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Regular meeting minutes, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Regular meeting minutes, 2000-2002 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Parish meeting minutes, 2006-2010 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Quarterly Winter Parish Meeting, January 25, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Trustees meeting minutes, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Reports, 1914-2005; 14 Items (13 folders, 1 volume)
    This subseries contains church and annual reports, as well as a single report from the 2005 National Association of Congregational Christian Churches meeting held in Kansas City
    - Church reports, 1914-1919 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Church reports, 1920-1922 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Church reports, 1923-1927 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Church reports, 1928-1930 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Church reports, 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Annual Report, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Annual Report, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Annual Report, 1950-1959 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    - Annual Report, 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Annual Report, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Annual Report, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Annual Report, 1977-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Annual Report, 1984-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Report from Kansas City NACCC meeting, June 26, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Auxiliary Organizations, 1899-1955, 1989-1996; 7 Items (4 folders, 3 volumes)
  This series contains records for several auxiliary organizations of the Grace North Church, such as the Ladies' Aid Society, the Bay Association, and the Grace Institute of Religious Learning.
  - Ladies' Aid Society, 1899-1924; 2 Items (2 volumes)
    This subseries contains meeting minutes and finances for the Ladies' Aid Society for the Grace North Church.
    - Ladies' Aid Meeting Minutes, 1899-1907 (Box 3, Volume 7)
    - Ladies' Aid Society finances, 1911-1924 (Box 3, Volume 8)
  - Bay Association, 1921-1955; 1 Item (1 volume)
    This subseries contains meeting minutes for the Bay Association of the Grace North Church.
    - Bay Association meeting minutes, 1921-1955 (Box 2, Volume 13)
  - Grace Institute of Religious Learning, 1989-1996; 4 Items (4 folders)
    This subseries contains the finances, bylaws, exemption applications, and the records of Rev. Richard Mapplebeckpalmer.
    - Grace Institute of Religious Learning finance reports and budget, 1989-1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Grace Institute of Religious Learning bylaws, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Grace Institute of Religious Learning exemption application, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Grace Institute of Religious Learning records of Rev. Richard Mapplebeckpalmer, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Finances, 1937-1973; 5 Items (5 volumes)
  This series contains financial ledgers from the church.
  - Financial Ledger, 1937-1944 (Box 6, Volume 1)
  - Financial Ledger, 1944-1950 (Box 6, Volume 2)
  - Financial Ledger, 1950-1956 (Box 6, Volume 3)
  - Financial Ledger, 1967-1971 (Box 5, Volume 2)
  - Financial Ledger, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Volume 3)
- Histories and Publications, 1942-1959, 1990-1998; 9 Items (8 folders, 1 volumes)
  - Scrapbook, 1942-1949 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - North Star Volume 8, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - North Star Volume 9, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - North Star Volume 11, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - History of Grace North Church with Exhibits, 1990-1998 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Formation of North Grace Church, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Celebrating the Centenary, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Last 25 Years of the North Congregational Church, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Brief histories of the church, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Building and Architecture, 1948-1966, 1995-2010; 9 Items (9 folders)
  - Congregational Church Building Society loans, 1948-1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence on Returning Title to North Grace Chruch, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Lease Agreements with National Association of Congregational Christian Churches, 1995-2001 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Application for Landmark Status, December 6, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Landmark Status Application, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sale of Church Building (1 of 4), 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sale of Church Building (2 of 4), 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sale of Church Building (3 of 4), 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sale of Church Building (4 of 4), 2009-2010 (Box 7, Folder 4)